Frederick Lewis Allen Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Frederick Lewis Allen Papers 1890-1954 (bulk 1933-1954)
MSS10470
Allen, Frederick Lewis
10,500 items 30 containers 12 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Editor and author. Correspondence, articles, biographies, date books, diaries, radio scripts, histories, and speeches documenting Allen's career as editor of Harper's Magazine, director of the Foreign Policy Association, author of many popular works on American social history, and an overseer of Harvard University.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Allen, Frederick Lewis, 1890-1954.; Allen, Hildegarde--Correspondence.; Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978--Correspondence.; De Voto, Bernard Augustine, 1897-1955--Correspondence.; Dean, Vera Micheles, 1903-1972--Correspondence.; Highet, Gilbert, 1906-1978--Correspondence.; Lippmann, Walter, 1889-1974--Correspondence.; McKinney, Laurence--Correspondence.; Perkins, Milo, 1900- --Correspondence.; Pfeiffer, George--Correspondence.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Wallace, DeWitt, 1889-1981--Correspondence.; Zuill, W. S. (William S.)--Correspondence.
Organizations
Foreign Policy Association.; Harvard University.
Subjects
American periodicals.; Industries--United States.; Journalism.
Places
London (England)--Description and travel.; San Francisco (Calif.)--Description and travel.; United States--History.; United States--Social conditions.
Titles
Harper's magazine.
Occupations
Authors.; Editors.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The papers of Frederick Lewis Allen, editor and author, were donated to the Library of Congress by his wife, Agnes Rogers Allen, and his son, Oliver E. Allen, between 1954 and 1996.
Additional Guides
A press release on the Frederick Lewis Allen Papers was issued by the Library of Congress on 22 September 1955, and an acquisitions note appeared in the Library's Information Bulletin, Vol. 14, No. 38 (19 September 1955), pp. 2-3. The collection was also described in the Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions, Vol. 13, No. 3 (May 1956), pp. 155-156.
Related Materials
Material on Allen can be found in the
Harper's Magazine Records
also housed in the Manuscript Division of the Library of Congress
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Frederick Lewis Allen are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1890, July 5 Born, Boston, Mass.
1912 B. A., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1912-1914 English instructor, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1913 M. A., Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1914-1916 Assistant editor, Atlantic Monthly
1916-1917 Managing editor, Century Magazine
1918 Married Dorothy Penrose (died 1930)
1918-1919 Member, Council of National Defense
1919-1923 Secretary to Harvard Corporation, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1923-1931 Assistant editor, Harper's Magazine
1931 Published Only Yesterday. New York: Harper & Brothers
1931-1941 Associate editor, Harper's Magazine
1932 Married Agnes Rogers Hyde
1933 Published with Agnes Rogers Allen The American Procession. New York: Harper & Brothers
1934 Published with Agnes Rogers Allen Metropolis. New York: Harper & Brothers
1935 Published The Lords of Creation. New York: Harper & Brothers
1937-1944 Trustee, Bennington College, Bennington, Vt.
1940 Published Since Yesterday. New York: Harper
1941-1953 Editor-in-chief, Harper's Magazine
1942-1948 Overseer, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1945-1950 Director, Foreign Policy Association
1947 Published I Remember Distinctly. New York: Harper
1949 Published The Great Pierpont Morgan. New York: Harper
1950-1954 Overseer, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1952 Published The Big Change. New York: Harper
1954, Feb. 13 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Frederick Lewis Allen span the years 1890-1954, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1933-1954. The papers are organized in five series: Diaries, Date Books, and Biographical Material; General Correspondence; Subject File; Literary File; and an Addition.
The Diaries, Date Books, and Biographical Material series covers the years 1933-1954 and includes diaries kept by Allen during visits to London in 1943 and to San Francisco in 1945.
The bulk of the General Correspondence focuses on the period 1945-1954 and includes letters written on a weekly basis by Allen to his sister, Hildegarde Allen. Correspondence relating to a particular literary work is kept with other papers related to that work in the Literary File. Prominent correspondents include James Bryant Conant, Vera Micheles Dean, Bernard Augustine DeVoto, Gilbert Highet, Walter Lippmann, Laurence McKinney, Milo Perkins, George Pfeiffer, DeWitt Wallace, and W. S. Zuill.
Included in the Subject File is material related to Allen's term as a member of the Board of Overseers of Harvard University, 1942-1948; his work with the Foreign Policy Association; and his speech to the National Publishers' Association in 1947 on the "closed mind" of journalists regarding American industry.
The Literary File contains manuscripts and notes related to Allen's writings, including popular social histories of the United States such as Only Yesterday and The Big Change, March of Time movie scripts about the 1920s, biographies, magazine articles, speeches, and other short works.
The Addition, consisting of material added to the papers in 1978, 1983, and 1996, supplements the original collection. A travel journal documenting Allen's trip to Great Britain in 1953 was added in 1996.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in five series:
Diaries, Date Books, and Biographical Material, 1933-1954
General Correspondence, 1913-1954
Subject File, 1946-1952
Literary File, 1930-1953
Addition, 1890-1954
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78010470
Container List
- Diaries, Date Books, and Biographical Material, 1933-1954 (Box 1)
  Pocket diaries, travel journals, and biographical sketches.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Biographical file, circa 1942-1954 (Box 1)
  - Diaries (Box 1)
    - England, 1943 (Box 1)
    - San Francisco, Calif., 1945 (Box 1)
  - Pocket diaries, 1933-1954, (22 vols.) (Box 1)
- General Correspondence, 1913-1954 (Box 1-6)
  Letters sent and received.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1913-1933 (Box 1)
  - 1934-1941, (9 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1942-1947, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - 1948-1950, (6 folders) (Box 4)
  - 1951-1952, (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1953-1954, undated, (5 folders) (Box 6)
- Subject File, 1946-1952 (Box 7)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, and topical files.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Foreign Policy Association, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., (3 folders) (Box 7)
- Literary File, 1930-1953 (Box 8-25)
  Drafts of books, magazine articles, speeches, scripts, and miscellaneous works.
  Arranged by type of material or work and therein by title or topic.
  - Articles (Box 8)
    - "Bermuda Base" (Box 8)
    - "Drafting This Army" (Box 8)
    - Life articles, (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous short works (Box 8)
    - Published articles by Allen, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Review of Whitaker Chambers's Witness (Box 9)
    - Woman's Home Companion articles (Box 9)
  - Books (Box 9)
    - The American Procession (Box 9)
    - The Big Change, (1 folder); (7 folders) (Box 9, Box 10)
    - The Great Pierpont Morgan, (4 folders); (3 folders) (Box 11, Box 12, Box 13)
    - I Remember Distinctly, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Lords of Creation, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Metropolis (Box 15)
    - Only Yesterday, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 15, Box 16)
    - Since Yesterday, (2 folders); (3 folders); (5 folders) (Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22)
    - Unpublished (Box 22)
      - "The American Tradition" (Box 22)
      - Roosevelt, Franklin D., notes and other material for an uncompleted book, (2 folders) (Box 22)
  - Documentary films and radio and television programs (Box 23)
    - "Golden Twenties," documentary film, (2 folders) (Box 23)
    - Ford television program (Box 23)
    - General plans for "Cowboys" radio program (Box 23)
    - Memorandum re possible subjects for a television series (Box 23)
    - Radio script of interview with Allen re Harper's Magazine's one hundred years of publication (Box 23)
  - Harper's Magazine file (Box 24)
  - Miscellany (Box 24)
  - Speeches and conferences (Box 24)
    - "Closed Mind," correspondence re speech on journalism and industry (Box 24)
    - "Economic Security: A Look Back And A Look Ahead," Economic Security for Americans, Columbia University, New York, N.Y. (Box 24)
    - Miscellany, (3 folders) (Box 25)
- Addition, 1890-1954 (Box 26-30)
  Journals, correspondence, writings, notes, printed matter, and clippings.
  - Journals (Box 26)
    - Journal about Allen as a baby by his father, Frederick B. Allen, 1890-1893 (Box 26)
    - Travel journals (Box 26)
      - Trip to Great Britain, 1953 (Box 26)
      - "Thomas Jefferson Book: Notes on How To Be More Like Thomas Jefferson," kept by Allen and Agnes Rogers Allen during trip from Scarsdale, N.Y., to Chapel Hill, N.C., 1936 (Box 26)
  - General correspondence (Box 26)
    - 1892-1908, (3 folders) (Box 26)
    - 1910-1935, (4 folders) (Box 27)
    - 1936-1954, undated, (2 folders) (Box 28)
  - Writings (Box 28)
    - Books (Box 28)
      - The Big Change drafts (Box 28)
        - Chapters 1-5, (2 folders) (Box 28)
        - Chapters 6-18, (4 folders) (Box 29)
        - Foreword, notes, research material (Box 30)
    - Short works and notes (Box 30)
      - Chronology of the 1930s and notes used for Since Yesterday (Box 30)
      - "Last Time and This Time: Postwar Eras I and II" (Box 30)
      - "President Ell" (Box 30)
      - "Three Years of It: America at War, 1941-1944" (Box 30)
      - "The State of the States" (Box 30)
      - "The Transformation of Suburbia" (Box 30)
      - "The Suburban Crisis" (Box 30)
      - "Who's Getting the Money?" (Box 30)
  - Miscellany (Box 30)
    - Book contracts (Box 30)
    - Printed matter (Box 30)
    - Clippings (Box 30)